Hello everyone and welcome back to
active inference insights. Today I have
the real pleasure of speaking to Ryan
Smith.
Ryan is a principal investigator at the
Laurier Institute for brain research and
he's the research associate professor at
Oxy College of Health Sciences at the
University of Tulsa.
His work focuses on the neuro
computational mechanisms underlying
emotion cognition interactions and how
they relate to brain body interactions
with special focus on planning,
information gain and interoceptive
inference. He's also the primary author
of probably the best known and most
highly rated tutorial on active
inference writing it alongside Carl
Friston and Christopher White.
Ryan, thank you for giving me your time.
Uh welcome to the show.
Thanks for thanks for having me. Excited
to get to talk.
No, it's it's an absolute pleasure. It's
it's it's really very exciting. As I
said, I mean
obviously I'd come across your work uh
kind of inevitably for me to have
invited you, but it was actually a real
treat to sort of go back and
go through like what feels like a you've
done loads and work at this incredible
velocity.
Um so it's been really fun to dive in
and and explore this
I guess what felt like a more empirical
side um cuz I'm spending most of my time
reading sort of philosophy papers. So it
was great to see some like traditional
statistics and some proper empirical
work. So so it's been a great it's been
great fun on my part.
I wanted to start at kind of a pretty
broad level and speak about subjective
well-being.
So you wrote this paper in 2022 sort of
grounding subjective well-being in the
parameters and mechanisms of active
inference.
Um
you alongside Casper Hesp of
Casper Hesp have come up with this
really nice way of grounding well-being
in expected free energy.
But as you write in that paper, you say
um while variational free energy can be
understood to track basic biological
fitness, this is neither necessary nor
sufficient for an individual to report
high subjective well-being. So, maybe
where we could start for the audience is
just explaining
why the minimization of variational free
energy is not sort of the simple
solution to obtaining high subjective
well-being.
Sure. Yeah, and I mean it's a definitely
a very kind of complicated and yeah,
complex complex topic jump into and it
honestly depends a little bit about the
exact kind of formalism that you're kind
of working in. I mean, me, I almost
exclusively work within the
sort of like POMDP formalism associated
with decision-making and planning
processes that uh
that you know, is the focus of our
tutorial and you know, and the focus of
the tutorial was very much like trying
to get people to a point of being able
to do true kind of experimental
empirical applications, right? I mean,
that's the final section is all kind of
meant to transition into that
just cuz that's primarily what I do.
Um, so
so, I mean, with respect to that kind of
um
yeah, your your question here is that
within the POMDP scheme,
you know, variational free energy is
primarily used as a means of optimizing
posterior beliefs about states, right?
So, it's a state inference um, sort of
process. Whereas, expected free energy
is the thing where you're trying to say,
okay, what do I expect the kind of
rewardingness of the outcomes to be and
how much information do I expect to
gain, you know, conditional on choosing
X versus Y. Um, so there there is a true
kind of valency thing, right? In the
expected free energy because you have
this expected divergence or lack thereof
between the things you want and the
things you expect, right? Under a
policy. Whereas, the variational free
energy is much more um, a function of is
just a function of the observations
you're getting and how you update
beliefs about the most sort of
appropriate um, approximate posterior
over those states, right? So, So, words,
you know, if I perceive that
uh, you know, if the observation I'm get
getting is that you know, someone's like
stabbing me or something.
Right? Then the the process I go through
to minimize variational free energy,
that that is what I use to infer that
the best interpretation of what's
happening to me is that I'm currently
being stabbed.
Right? So, so if if the idea with
variational free energy as it is at
least in in the kind of standard POMDP
formalism
is a way of just getting at the best
posterior belief about the state you're
in, then that state could be something
you really like or something you really
don't like, right?
Cool.
Um so, so just when you when you see it
that way, um
then there is this kind of big
distinction between trying to um
trying to maximize
um the consistency between your
preferred observations and the
observations you think you're going to
get. Um that that's just that's valency
and could relate to well-being um in a
much more direct way than just trying to
optimize your beliefs about the current
states you're in.
Right. It's interesting that yeah, you
you focus more on the sort of perceptual
side of variational free energy
uh cuz at least the way that I've spoken
about it and I've seen written and I've
and I've written is that it's kind of
it's kind of jewel wieldy in the sense
that variational free energy being this
uh kind of upper bound on
self-information or surprisal, you can
also minimize it by taking action.
But then that said, when we talk about
action, we always frame it within
expected free energy terms.
So, I've been kind of thinking just
again, this is just a completely sort of
nascent, not really fleshed out thought
is that
action seems to do can do
variational free energy and expected
free energy minimization at the same
time
in the sense that you know, if you're
uh sort of
maximization of model evidence term, the
the minus log of
the probability of Y,
if you're doing that also your you're
maximizing pragmatic value, it seems
like you're doing both at the same time.
Is it kind of a an erroneous way of
thinking to allied or combine expected
free energy and variational free energy
in this way?
Um yeah, I mean like I said, it's a
little bit complex because I mean um so
So okay, what's the right way to put
this?
Um
certainly um in the uh you know, what
the the accuracy of the expected free
energy calculation that you do, right,
depends, right, on whether you have good
posterior beliefs over states. Um and it
depends on whether you're updating your
actual generative model appropriately
based on the patterns of observations
you're getting over time,
um which would correspond to what we
typically call learning, right, as
opposed to perception. Um so obviously,
your expected free energy estimates will
not be good if your model is really bad.
Um and so there's an indirect
dependence, right, on our ability to
maximize um being in the states that we
want to be in. Um there's a dependence
between that and using the um and
minimizing variational free energy, at
least in a way that um um and of of
course that depends on whether you're
very minimizing variational free energy
with respect to a a model that's in fact
accurate, right? I mean, you can get an
approximate posterior belief that
minimizes variational free energy
um
with respect to a model, but if your
model is very mismatched with the world,
then
Right.
um that approximate posterior is still
not going to be a good description of
the world, and therefore you might still
end up getting observations you really
don't want
Yeah.
when you choose policies based on that,
right? So
Right.
um you know, that being said, I mean,
you know, it's a little bit the way you
formalize it because um
the you know, often when it's kind of
talked about more generically,
especially in the philosophy literature,
um yeah, I definitely variational free
energy has the kind of dual, right,
perception-action
aspect, but um um
but there there isn't really like a I
mean the the tricky thing is is that
action, at least when action is formed
in the kind of explicit planning
decision-making sense,
you still do require
some kind of cost function, right? You
still have to have some mechanism that
says, "I expect action A to be better
than action B."
Sure.
Um
and and free energy is a function of
current observations, right? Whereas the
the planning and decision-making kind of
has to be with respect to future
observations.
Yes.
And that's kind of the distinction
between variational and expected free
energy. Um now now I say that in
addition, however, I mean you so you
mentioned the thing that me and Casper
had done with that, you know, deeply
felt affect paper. And in in there there
is this kind of further further term
that can be added into the into the
active inference formalism if you want
to. It doesn't always kind of have to be
there. It depends on the you know,
context of the sort of task or cognitive
process you you care about um or that
you're trying to model, but um
where you you are effectively comparing
the expected free energy to the
variational free energy
with the new observation that you get,
right? And so there either will be a
match or a mismatch there.
Right.
So if it's the case, for example, and
under with that example, if it's the
case that the um
the expected free energy is gets a
little mathy, but but the expected free
energy vector over over policies, if
that kind of geometrically if if that
vector points in a direction that is
consistent with
the variational free energy of the
observations that you get,
Right.
then you can kind of think of that as
being a little bit kind of like a
positive reward prediction error. It's
basically saying that what you got was
um consistent with and even sort of
better than expected um compared to G.
So it's kind of like F F matches with G
or is consistent with G or maybe even a
little better.
Nice.
And and that in the in the deep belief
active formalism, the idea was that that
that sort of positive prediction that
positive reward prediction error
effectively can itself be treated as an
observation that can kind of feed into a
higher level model.
Mhm.
Where it's kind of like evidence for a a
positive affective state.
Right.
that can kind of put a prior back down
on what that what that kind of expected
value is for
um the parameter associated with that,
which is just this
beta hyper prior thing.
And then you know the function the
function of that though is interesting,
right? Cuz in the in the reverse
direction you can also have F disagree
with G, right? Which which would just
mean that right, your expected free
energy was based on a bad model
essentially.
Right.
Um and so and so you know in that case
uh you would expect that there'd be a a
negative affective response. Um and so
that would act act for act as evidence
for this higher level model that would
say, "Okay, I'm in a that's evidence for
a negative affective state." But what
that
what that beta term ends up doing,
right? So when you negative affective
state corresponds to that beta value
getting bigger,
um
which ends up being
what it what it does is a little bit
um is a little bit nuanced as well
though because if you don't assume that
there's any kind of initial habit-like
prior beliefs over policies then um
effectively all the beta does is just
add noise to choice. Um you can think
about it kind of like a random
exploration term in like in a like in
reinforcement learning, but it's just
kind of saying like trust your expected
free energy less.
Right.
Therefore therefore select actions a
little bit more randomly from your
posterior distribution over policies.
Sure.
But, if you instead happen to have
precise
habits, right? So, you've just the last
50 times, you know, you were in this
situation, you chose option two.
Mhm.
Then and it's kind of assumed implicitly
that that must have worked out well,
right? If you kept doing it over and
over again. Then then if beta gets big,
then it ends up essentially favoring the
influence of habits over
what the expected free energy would say.
So, in that case, it kind of implies
that when you're in a negative affective
state, you'll become more kind of habit
driven.
And so, that's that's a little bit the
way that that the dynamics end up
working.
Okay, excellent. Yeah, yeah, yeah. So,
maybe just for myself and the audience,
I'm going to try and do a
sort of paraphrasing slash just trying
to align what what's going up and
Sure.
What kind of what's going up and what's
going down?
Yeah.
So,
I'm familiar with the gamma parameter.
Yeah.
The gamma parameter being sort of a
scale of expected free energy estimates.
So, it kind of tracks in the way how
confident the system is in its action
model. That's the way that I think about
it.
beta is just a hyperparameter on that.
It's just the inverse of that. One over
beta is gamma.
Okay. Okay, so that's so that's really
useful. So, the way that I thought about
it is that if you've got lower values of
gamma,
that means the system has lower
confidence in sort of its capacity to do
expected free energy, and so it's going
to lean towards habits.
Sure.
Just so I'm aware that that means that
it's high
beta.
Got it. Okay, so have you seen
this new George Dean paper that came out
and the preprint came out what last
week? Something like this. It's a
wonderful paper. It's about sort of
canalized psychopathalogical
behavior. So, very much in line with
what you're writing about.
Okay.
And exactly what they say, you So, you
can sort of treat
gamma itself as a hidden state.
Mhm.
And you can maximize your mental act you
can sort of optimize your mental action
so as to kind of optimize gamma in a
way. So, it kind of looks like again,
I'm going to avoid thinking about met
certain memories
or I'm going to avoid thinking about
expected, you know, a potential future
Mhm.
because that will lead I know that will
lead to reduced gamma.
A lower estimate of my capacity to do
expected free energy. I may be
butchering this.
Um
Yeah, I feel I feel I feel a little
limited just because I haven't read the
paper, so I yeah, I might not be able to
comment confidently on all of that.
sure. Well, I just wanted to mention it
in any case cuz it's it's a nice
addition to this picture.
Sure. Yeah, and I mean for an R and
yeah, all I can all I can really kind of
say is is that yeah, for for us or at
least the way that we've been we've
thought about it previously is is that
gamma gamma itself is is
is not like sort of directly hidden
state itself, but it is like an
observation that can act as
it's it's a thing that can be treated as
an observation to inform inference over
hidden states at a higher level.
Nice.
So, you have all of this kind of higher
level that's has a posterior of am I
okay am I in a positive affective state
or am I in a negative affective state
and that current and that the change in
gamma after a new observation is one
piece of evidence
for changing the positive or negative
affective state. Um two things that I
think they're they're kind of important
there. If if we're talking about it that
way, again, that's just my idea, but if
we're talking about it that way, one is
is that
crucially that kind of implies that it's
not the only thing that can act as
evidence for for the emotional state
here.
Yep.
Right. So, you could have lots of other
things besides just this kind of
positive or negative prediction error
thing that that influences, right? Like
I mean, I think that things about your
interoceptive state, right? Like, are
probably important for that.
Um among among other things, right? So,
so I just
I wouldn't I just personally wouldn't
want to commit myself to saying that
like it's gamma and only gamma is
directly, right? This this thing.
Um because the because in in that
formalism what ends up happening is is
just whatever your current belief is at
the higher level about your affective
state ends up putting a prior back on
what gamma is. Right? So, it's like So,
when I'm in a negative affective state,
you know, going forward on the next
trial or the next time I have to make a
choice, that thing is pushing gamma
down.
Right.
Um Now, I mean, something something that
I do probably want to highlight though
is is is that I I doubt that that's the
complete story um for for at least a
couple of reasons. One one big one is
that empirically um
negative affective states um while they
are
consistent consistent with what um
consistent with what uh
would be kind of suggested here,
negative affective states
track something like lack of confidence
in a model.
Mhm.
That being said, um
typically what that tends to look like
in a lot of other sorts of modeling
frameworks and some empirical results is
is that the main effect that that has
isn't really to make decision making
noisier, but actually to like turn up
information seeking and to turn up
learning rate.
Right.
Right? So, it makes sense that if I
don't think my model's very good, then I
ought to kind of turn up my learning
rate so I update my beliefs faster
um you know, from the next sequence of
events that I experience because I
shouldn't be trusting my model. Well, so
it's kind of like, "Okay, I got to hurry
up and change my model to make it
accurate again." Um and and kind of
influence of learning rate doesn't
directly follow from anything about
gamma.
Um
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, that's
more I've been thinking about this a
little bit as well in terms of
canalization. That's more kind of this
negotiation between the B matrix and the
A matrix.
Um
Potentially.
I mean, well, that might be one part of
it, right? If I've got particularly
imprecise uh
B matrices, let's say cuz I have some
dopaminergic
um
synaptic misfiring, and so I have
hyperprecision over A,
then I'm going to mistrust these state
transitions more than the norm, let's
say.
Yeah, I guess I guess the thing that
probably matters here is this is that um
depending on the context that you're
trying to model, um
there's very different things that you
might need to be There's very different
parts of your model that you might
either want to be or not wanting to be
updating.
Right.
Right. So, so So, if So, maybe, right,
what I'm not confident in is something
about my beliefs about state
transitions.
Um and in that case, I want to be
effectively or directly updating my
learning rate about the transition
probabilities.
Right.
Right. So, I'm going to like pay
attention to the coincidences between
state and next state over and over again
to kind of like reoptimize that.
Whereas, if if the thing that I'm
um
not confident about is something more
about my likelihood function, right?
More about the mapping between states to
observations,
um then I ought to be changing the kind
of rate at which I change my beliefs
about that likelihood function.
Right.
Now, you know, how do you do that itself
is tricky, like I said. I think I think
a more kind of extended formalism would
need to be um
put together if we were going to try to
turn gamma into something that also
affected that. Um
But, um but it also I don't know. One
One kind of tricky thing, I guess, is is
that um
in a lot of the kind of practical
modeling applications right now, um the
way that learning is um
learning rate is adjusted is just via
kind of fixed parameter
that's just essentially just a scalar on
the
on the updates to the
to the the counts and the the counts
that are added to the Dirichlet
distributions
for you know A or B or you know whatever
whatever one you're happen to you happen
to be modeling learning at a given time,
but it's a little bit I mean it it's
similar to you know including these
sorts of constants um the way you do in
like a standard kind of reinforcement
learning model
but it's not quite the same as the way
you might um
do it if you were being kind of like
trying to be fully true to Bayesian
learning
um because
because in in if you were kind of going
true Bayesian learning completely you
didn't want to have a kind of like ad
hoc constant you know that just kind of
scales the updates
um then it it ought to be something that
follows from the relative precisions of
the um your prior and your and the
signal coming from the likelihood right?
um and um
you can do that um
but and if you assume a kind of constant
sensory input and a constant likelihood
then you would learn more from that um
signal given that you had flatter versus
sharper priors over states which would
follow from your transition beliefs and
therefore your kind of you know B matrix
quote unquote but um
that actually kind of when we we've
tried to do it in the past it works but
it's hard to make it work without um
making a model hierarchical or at least
kind of making it kind of implicitly
hierarchical
Yes.
it's a little tricky but it it formally
the the reason for that is is that you
um
in the current schemes observations are
kind of treated as things that are
um
kind of fully like one hot vector like
it's a you know a one and a bunch of
zeros basically. There's no uncertainty
about the observation. Where the
uncertainty comes in is just what state
you should believe you're in given that
observation. But to to get the kind of
learning that I'm talking about, you
need to actually have the the the the
observe
To do it right in some ways, you have to
actually have the observation vector
itself have some noise in it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Um
the cross, right? And so that happens
naturally in a hierarchical model
because the the first level states do
have noise in them and they act as
observations for the second level.
I see.
But but also, you know, for practical
applications, you can just kind of
pretend your model is effectively
hierarchical by just having it be single
level but make the observations
uh
noisy as opposed to being one hot
vectors and that actually does the same
thing.
Yeah. Well, I was thinking of the other
way that um to control these learning
rates, you would need something like a
metacognitive aspect.
Uh
Yeah, you could do something like that,
too. You could have like a higher level
like a second level state that
sort of conditional on that. Whatever
that is, it modulates the learning rate
at the level below.
Well, let me go back to this um this
George paper just cuz again, I'm I'm
quite concerned for some reason on well,
not for some reason. It's for good
intellectual honesty that I don't
misspeak and I don't uh you know
So and I'm sort of curious again about
what you
think. So I've just got it up here. They
say
Yeah, so in effective inference, the
system not only possesses an estimate of
action model confidence described as
implicitly metacognitive, but at the not
another layer of the generative model
can be added so that the confidence
estimate itself becomes a hidden state
that the system infers using the same
mechanics of perceptual inference.
So that's kind of similar to in a sense
what I was saying, right? The the gamma
itself is becoming the hidden state. But
I think what they're the point that
they're making there is that you're not
just doing
perceptual updating, you're also doing
planning as inference.
Mhm.
So, you can do, in terms of mental
action, attentional schemes, you can
deploy certain mental actions such that
the observations you make are going to
be either, you know, increasing the
likelihood of being in that hidden state
or not.
Mhm.
And that's what, you know, that's
whe- whether that's thinking about
something that's good bad that's going
to happen in the future or something bad
that happened in the past, you're more
likely to avoid thinking those things
because you're aware that
probabilistically you might end up in
low gamma.
Yeah, that's interesting. I guess
there's a few different things here
where I'm just I I don't know. I mean,
my initial go-to when I start talking
about all of this is kind of like how I
would like, you know, write it down, you
know,
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
make it kind of, you know, work
formally. And so, there's kind of like a
few different things are kind of mixed
together in there. Um so, I mean, like
one one thing I could totally see, which
I thought was what you were talking
about a second ago, was was like um
instead of the
gamma-based kind of hierarchical
updating thing that we were talking
about before, like that kind of
second-level state, part of its
likelihood back down to the first level
could also be something about like the
the learning rate.
Mhm.
Right? So, it could directly through
this kind of additional connection in
the second-level likelihood, you know,
when I'm in a negative affective state,
turn up the turn up the learning rate at
the lower level.
Um
which isn't so like so much intentional
or kind of like controlled per se,
right? It's just something that kind of
like happens automatically as a function
of whatever you infer your affect
affective state is. Um that's just a
little different, I suppose, from if you
built in
a policy itself
that controlled something like the like
transitions to like attentional states.
Yes, so
that We've done that in some of our like
emotion inference models, right? Where
you can kind of you could kind of
selectively choose, okay, now I'm going
to pay attention to my current valence.
All right, now I'm going to pay
attention to my arousal level.
Um where you can kind of
use a second hidden state factor to kind
of like pull out slices of the
likelihood tensor that that encode the
precision of the observations.
Um
um with respect to the mapping to a
different hidden state factor.
Um but uh but so there's there's all
that kind of thing. You don't actually
need explicit hierarchy for that. You
just kind of need separate orthogonal
state factors like in practice, but um
but yeah, so you could do that. And then
the third thing I guess that makes me
think of is is something that I I I
played around with a little bit that I
think is actually a really cool idea,
but haven't done anything really with is
that um
you can try to account for like what can
still be like I kind of like Bayesian
form of like motivated cognition that
would look kind of biased in the outside
by um
you know, cuz if if in a second-level
model you're um you're treating the
first-level states as observations for
the second level, then that means like
you can have a prior preference
distribution over first-level states,
right? So then effectively like you
actually just like want to believe some
things and not others.
Right.
Yeah, so if you want to believe some
things and not others, then like the
optimal policy um will could be
something that looks super anti-Bayesian
from a fully like epistemic perspective.
Sure.
But probably Bayes optimal under the
actual scheme that you've got in place.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly. Right? But
but externally, right?
Well, yes, I mean this is exactly the
point I'm coming to. They they speak of
sort of avoidant mental action or
motivated inattention.
Right.
Um and this idea is that you're kind of
performing the second-order inference
over the model precision, as I said. But
you have this kind of predictive model
with model precision as the hidden
state, such that I mean the way they
talk about it is how will I feel if I do
that but with respect to mental action.
Sure.
Which I think is very I don't know. I
just thought it was very cool and very
much up your
Yeah, absolutely. I mean, yeah, when it
comes to the affective stuff, I totally
agree. Like I said, I'm super interested
in this. I mean, it uh
I mean, in part it makes me like like I
both think it's really cool and it also
makes me slightly like empirically
uncomfortable.
And the the reason for that is is that
like I'm pretty sure it makes like
like actually testing like whether a
model like this is kind of like the the
best model of human behavior. Basically,
I think it makes it kind of
unfalsifiable.
Right. Right. Right. Right. Well, well,
let's let's jump into that then. I mean,
you when we got you spoke on email, you
were keen to
Cuz that one can account for basically
anything.
you when we got you spoke on email, you
were keen to sort of mention that you're
not just doing pure simulation work.
And you're doing empirical what you call
well, I think what is called empirical
computational psychiatry whereby fit
models to behavioral data in clinical
populations.
Which is super cool, but I'm not a
mathematician. So, and I assume a lot of
the audience aren't mathematicians
either. So, perhaps you could just in
sort of a broad brush approach describe
the distinction between
uh pure simulation work and empirical
computational psychiatry.
Yeah, I mean, I guess
I think the the cool part about doing
simulation stuff is that is that you're
like pretty under constrained, right?
Like like there's a there's a kind of
like creativity about it and you can
kind of get really complicated and you
know, it allows you to kind of simulate
some cool mechanisms. Um
but a lot of times like the the concern
I suppose is that they become a lot of
like just so stories in a sense, right?
Like because you know, I could come up
with probably like 10 different
generative models that would uh you you
that would hypothesize somewhat
different mechanisms,
um, but they would produce all the kind
of like behavioral signatures of the
sort of thing we're trying to explain,
right?
Right.
So, so I think it's important to be able
to find ways to actually, you know,
test, you know, which of these models
are actually good, you know, like
accurate descriptions of what's actually
going on in the brain.
Right.
And, um, and so, you know, for that,
right, you need to get these models to
have direct contact with data somehow.
Um, and, um, and so usually, you know,
so the sort of thing that, you know, we
will do, and I I well, I should say
another thing is is that um, you know,
like how good a model fits data, um,
is always a relative comparison,
right? I mean, you can't there are
absolute metrics of model fit, but
usually, you want to kind of say, "Okay,
here's a space of possible generative
models,
um, you know, that that hypothesize
different sorts of algorithms that are
being used or or or different just model
structures, but that assume, you know,
underlying the same underlying
algorithm." Um,
and then you kind of want to and you
want to do like Bayesian model
comparison, right? You just want to say,
"Out of all these models,
which model does the data provide the
most evidence for?"
Um,
and, you know, like that that actually
allows you to be able to test whether or
not like an active inference model, um,
or what an active inference model would
a given active inference model would
predict, um, you know, actually
reproduces the behavior that people
actually do, right?
Right.
Um, and, um, so so I just don't Yeah, I
mean, to be to be scientific about it, I
just wouldn't want or I think I think
it's important that for people to take
for for people outside of just the kind
of like active inference community
proper, right, to actually kind of take
these things seriously and think that
they're moving
um, moving science forward, um,
that uh, you know, we need to be able to
actually show that these things are
improving, right? How well we can
predict
what brain and behavior actually look
like compared to lots of other simpler
models that have been around for, you
know, much longer than active inference.
All right, so so I mean, you know,
computational psychiatry is a fairly
it's fairly new field, but you know,
there's a lot of there's more and more
people working in it, but most of them
are not um coming from like an active
inference background, you know, they
more tend to focus on simpler
reinforcement learning models
um that um
you know, at the end of the day don't
tend to be really too different in what
they predict from from active inference
in a lot of cases.
Um so it, you know, the trick is kind
of, you know, finding the right kinds of
decision-making or behavioral or
perceptual tasks to have people to have,
you know, participants coming and do,
whether they be healthy or whether they
be patient groups um to try to um you
know, to see In other words, you have to
find tasks where it's clear that a
particular active inference model would
actually make different predictions
Sure.
than a simpler um reinforcement learning
model. And um you know, we've started to
do quite a bit more of that. I am, you
know, there's a you know, for anyone for
anyone who wants to come, little plug,
uh the um one of my uh current grad
students um is uh presenting um well,
she's just about to submit for a talk or
a poster um for the computational
psychiatry conference um this summer in
Minneapolis in July. Um and it's uh and
this has been kind of our most thorough
attempt at this um lately as we just
have a a fairly simple like
explore-exploit
um sort of like three-armed bandit task
that involves tradeoffs between
information-seeking and reward-seeking,
and so it does kind of match, right,
where where active inference is supposed
to kind of show show its strengths with
that directed exploration. Um in this
case primarily with respect to the uh
novelty term, right? So, this would be
like parameter exploration, not state
exploration. Um,
but um but so, more or less we have
identified, I think, like this is like
table essentially of um
something like
30 different possible RL models and like
30 different equivalent equivalent
complexity active inference model,
something like This is a really massive
model space.
Um, and you know, fit all these models
to um to the um
to behavioral data in a couple hundred
people. Um, and both a both a Taiwanese
sample actually and an American sample.
Um,
and um and just done model comparison
across these. Um,
and um and the the models that tend to
win are more complicated models. Um,
there's a the the two the two kind of
best models in what we found so far. One
is
one is an active inference model that
assumes um that people have um
one forgetting rate um and two separate
learning rates for wins and losses um
separately. So, basically you update
your beliefs more or less when you get a
win versus when you get a loss. Um,
and then a kind of like dynamic decision
noise um sort of term that um is based
on the the beta thing actually, based on
the uh based on the um
updates of the uh the beta gamma
um term that we're talking about. Where
where effectively what that ends up
meaning is that um
when people
uh
get an outcome that's unexpected, right?
Then gamma goes down and so the
posterior probability flattens out and
so essentially their choices become more
exploratory in the in the randomness
sense um when they get outcomes that
they weren't expecting.
Right.
If they were negative. If they get
outcomes that are better than expected
and it's positive, then they become sort
of more deterministic in going with with
what the model would say is the best
choice. Um, and so that's the best like
active inference model that tends to
fit. So, it's very complex. It has like
five or six parameters, something like
that.
Um and the the winning RL model is
slightly different. It assumes dynamic
learning as opposed to dynamic
forgetting or I mean as opposed to
dynamic decision noise. Um
but the the point is that the main the
main difference between these models
ends up not really so much being
differences in exploratory behavior so
much as whether or not they include um
uh Bayesian forms of learning. Um
Right. Right. Right.
the main thing that the main thing that
active inference does that's really
different when you match it to kind of
an equivalent complexity RL model is um
is that
active inference models are kind of with
the with the Dirichlet distributions,
again, the details of that don't matter
for non-mathematical people. It just
basically means that in an RL model,
you're just kind of updating your
beliefs about the expected um reward
probabilities, whereas in active
inference, you're keeping track of those
reward probabilities, but also you're
keeping track of your confidence in
those beliefs about the reward
probabilities. Um and um and so that's
what um the
the kind of take home with it for for
what for what she's done is um mainly
that the um the ability for the two
models to um predict behavior is
actually at the best two models um is
actually fairly similar, but Bayesian
model comparison does um select the
active inference model over the
over the uh RL model. Um and because the
differences in accuracy between the
models aren't uh
aren't amazingly different, um ends up
relating probably a little bit more to
like complexity cost differences um and
you know, kind of evaluation of the
independent, like how independent each
parameter is in explaining the behavior,
things like that. Um so so anyway, I
mean, so a lot of what we've been doing
is kind of attempting to say, "Okay,
well, you know, how much better,
you know, does active inference actually
do, right, in explaining and explaining
behavior behavior? Is it the kind of
most parsimonious
accurate explanation for
um how people actually do make decisions
in in information seeking
So, that's a little bit, you know,
where, you know, kind of the approach
that we take. So, that and then using
those things
by also having people in patient groups
with like depression or anxiety or
substance use disorders
do these same sorts of tasks and then
see whether um
you know, we can explain
clinically relevant differences in
these, you know, between patients and
healthy comparisons
through differences in the actual
parameter estimates, right? So, maybe
it's the case that So, what one thing
that we have found, right? Is this is
that pretty consistently substance users
in active inference models tends to show
much slower learning rates from negative
outcomes
than positive outcomes. So, they kind of
it takes a lot more times of them
choosing a suboptimal thing before they
kind of change what they do.
Um
I found that I found that an interesting
result. Your 2023 paper, elevated
decision uncertainty and reduced
avoidance drives in depression, anxiety,
and substance use disorders. I maybe
that's a different one, but yeah.
This might be slightly different, but I
found maybe maybe I misinterpreted what
you said there, but this idea that
individuals at least with substance use
disorders show a reduced sensitivity to
unpleasant stimuli.
Yeah, okay. So, so it's Yeah, so there's
a Yeah, so that's a that's a with a
different task. Um it's actually the
same the same sample, but it's a
different task.
I guess the prior one is learning rates,
right? The first one is learning
Yeah, so it's kind of depends, right?
The learning rate one again, that's with
like a bandit task and so it's it is
about kind of explore-exploit, updating
beliefs about reward probabilities, etc.
whereas the
the approach-avoidance conflict task is
a little different. It's not a learning
task. It's purely just kind of a
planning forward-looking task.
And in that one, it's more or less
there's a different kind of number of,
you know, points that you know, people
can win, but they have to also choose to
go through some pretty unpleasant affect
of seeing some pretty seeing and hearing
some pretty unpleasant pleasant affect
of stimuli at the same time. So, you're
going to have to plan whether okay, do I
prefer to kind of move toward the side
of this runway that means the
probability is higher I'll kind of get
the safe neutral outcome but no points
or whether I'll whether I expect it to
be kind of worth it to me, right? To
like under a certain point value
try to act in a way that will increase
the probability that I'll get the points
but also see the super unpleasant stuff.
Right.
And and in that case, there's
you know, I mean this is sort of task
that's been used in non-computational
modeling way several times in the past
but the the main kind of metric, if you
don't do it the computational way, is
more or less just this general kind of
unidimensional approach-avoidance thing.
Whereas the the modeling version is a
little bit more helpful because we can
estimate the beta parameter for these
people and then we can also estimate
certain things about the shape of their
preference distribution.
And
and what that shows so we can kind of
use that to dissociate two different
aspects of approach-avoidance conflict.
One is this kind of like uncertainty
about decisions and the other is this
actual kind of, you know,
approach-avoidance drive.
Right.
And yeah, the results for that are
actually kind of surprising, you know,
cuz like in the in the depression and
anxiety and in the substance users,
they tend to show
greater just the patients tend to show
greater decision uncertainty so they
have higher beta values but they they
actually show
more precise preferences for the for the
points which basically means that
they're means that they're kind of more
willing to go through the negative
affect stuff.
I was very surprised by that.
Yeah, so they're actually less avoidant,
right? So, they're more uncertain but
they're less avoidant and that's we've
now shown that in four studies, you
know, so it's a very consistent result
across multiple samples.
I read that and I had to read it twice
uh because I was really like I really
expected the other
way around because we're used to hearing
that avoidance is the kind of number one
driver of a psychological disorder like
generalized anxiety disorder or
OCD. So, what
what do you imagine is going on here? I
mean, I think one it just talking in
terms of very layman non-computational
terms.
Yeah.
There's there's the overexposure of
people with psychological disorders to
negative stimuli in the first place.
Mhm.
So, what's negative for a
healthy control
is
well, it's all relative, right? And if
you've been exposed to overtly negative
things like your own emotions over and
over again,
maybe you have a reduced sensitivity.
Yeah, I mean, there's you know, I mean,
we don't we don't really have like
unfortunately, I mean, our our
hypothesis going in was absolutely what
you said originally, right? That we
would get more avoidance in the patient
groups. Um but uh you know, we were just
hoping that the the modeling would help
us kind of distinguish these couple
different kind of dimensions, right? Of
of of approach-avoidance conflict. Um
but uh but definitely we didn't expect
the the more approachy stuff in uh in
the in the patient groups. Um
that being said, yeah, so we So, because
of that, we don't have kind of a bunch
of other we don't have all the measures
that we probably would have gotten um to
try to dissociate different possible
explanations for that kind of unexpected
avoidance uh or unexpected lack of
avoidance.
Um
so, it becomes a little speculative, but
um one thing is absolutely, I mean,
that's one thing you might you might
suspect is what you said that um
you know, if if people uh if people are
just in general are in this kind of
heightened negative affective state,
then you know, you might expect that
makes them more sensitive to other
negative affective things, but you also
might make that also might think they're
a little bit habituated to it.
Yes, exactly. What would that look like
in terms of a kind of palm DP scheme cuz
I guess we associate habits with action.
Mhm.
With the prior value over or prior
beliefs over action. When we're talking
about habituated
uh responses to stimuli, I mean I guess
it is it's in the sense action.
But what what shape does that take?
Um yeah, I mean so so like I said in in
the official model that we were fitting,
it doesn't really include any include
the dynamics of habituation. We're just
kind of estimating the what the shape of
their preference distribution is, right?
That would explain their behavior.
Um and so it so then the explanation
just ends up being that they have a more
precise
preference for for winning the points or
or
or a less the the the the magnitude of
the the probability of the negative
outcomes in the preference distribution,
which again doesn't really mean
probability. It just means they
they disprefer the negative stuff less,
right? Um is uh is um you know, that
ends up explaining it, but um but um
but what would it look like if you
included some sort of actual learning
dynamics for um for habituation?
Um I mean so this kind of habituation is
is really not so much more about
habitual action as it is just the level
of sensitivity you have to stimuli,
right? So
Yes.
So it's a little more has this flavor of
okay, if I see something over and over
again, then my response to it each time
is less, right? So
so um
I think you could call I think you could
call that in terms of action.
Um
it it
Well, I mean so okay, so
I'm thinking in terms of traditional
therapeutic responses, right? Like in
terms of exposure and response
prevention therapy, for example.
You would you would at least have an
element of it which said that
uh
dysfunctional avoidance response
Again, this is a non-active inference
way of framing it, but just in a layman
sense, it entrenches
the
the severity or the perception of the
severity of the stimulus.
Yeah, so I mean, we have
you know, I don't know. I mean, I
wouldn't necessarily have expected you
to see it, but if you happen to, I mean,
we do have this paper we published a
couple years ago as a simulation paper
specifically on mechanisms of
possible mechanisms of CBT and in a home
base. So, we actually did simulate
exposure therapy in particular. Nice. Um
and
but it was the crucial kind of thing we
were looking for there was whether or
not we could kind of capture
make predictions about the ways that
cognitive interventions like reappraisal
would interact with behavioral
interventions like exposure therapy.
Um and
and I mean, some of some of some of that
we ended up being kind of kind of
excited about. It seemed consistent with
results or with Yeah, when I talked to
clinicians cuz I work with a lot of
clinicians.
You know, what they say about where
where with that, I mean, the the kind of
you know, habituation was much more
about like So,
if a person has a strong if a person has
a strong expectation that like if they
choose a certain action, then the things
they are going to observe are things
that they really don't like, right? So,
things that have a very low
preference level.
Then, you know, it follows all else
being equal, they're not going to
they're going to take actions that don't
lead them to those to make those
observations, right? But the problem is
is that when those when those
when those
uh
uh beliefs about the expected outcomes
of actions are are wrong, right? Then,
if they just avoid it every time, right?
Then, they can never they can never
update their beliefs, right? So, I mean,
exposure is essentially kind of this
kind of like
uh
clinician-facilitated
directed exploration, right?
Right, right, right.
you know, they kind of push you to go
take this action, right? That's going to
make you see, okay, what actually
happens when I'm in this state that I've
been avoiding. Um and so and so the kind
of habituation in that sense just ends
up being once they start actually seeing
what observations they really get
Yeah.
avoiding, then they just, you know, they
just update their likelihood function,
Right. Right. Right.
expect under that state. Um but um but
the the interesting thing at least in in
that paper was a lot more of how that
interacts with um your um cognitive
beliefs.
So, because because you can also, and
this is often what happens, right? Is
this is that when when people go through
exposure therapy,
um they will they can um even after
those respond the negative responses
kind of go away and they start to say,
okay, now now I believe like in the
context of spider phobia, for example,
like, no, okay, actually, you know, I
believe the spider is safe now. Right?
And so their responses their affective
responses like died down. But you know,
you bring them back in a couple days
later, they see the spider and they have
the negative responses again.
Sure.
Right? So it doesn't kind of like stick
around. It doesn't generalize. Um you
know, and so why is that, right? Because
under a simple
under a simple kind of like unlearning
story, um
they would have just overwritten their
old likelihood function, right? So they
shouldn't right? Their generative models
should be different. They shouldn't have
those responses again. Um you know, so
what explains that? Well, what explains
that has to be that they um that they
don't take evidence they don't take the
evidence from the unexpected outcomes
when they see a spider um as evidence
that their likelihood function was
wrong. They take it instead as evidence
that they've actually transitioned to to
a new hidden hidden state context.
Ah.
So that now so now they believe, okay, I
am in the safe context.
And then they just update their
likelihood under the safe context.
Ah, that's interesting.
Right. So then all you have to do is
say, "Okay, well, if there's any
uncertainty in the transition function,
then even though they believe they're in
the safe context now, come back in a
couple days later, there's more
uncertainty over what context they're
in. So their responses come back because
the likelihood function under the danger
context still says, right, bad things
will happen if spider."
So how would you resolve that?
Um yeah, so so it um
I mean, so one thing you want to do then
is you want to you want to try your best
as a as a therapist in some way to um to
not use cognitive approaches to try to
like make people believe, "Oh, actually,
this is really, you know, this is really
safe, right?"
yeah.
You're going to go in this room, you're
going to see the spider, but it is safe,
right? Like you have to have them
actually maintain some kind of
uncertainty about what context they're
in.
Right.
Um cuz only in that case, if there's
like a like in the simulations, more or
less, like I always showed is like
if you keep the posterior distribution
that they have about the context they're
in, if you kind of keep that imprecise,
right, if you maintain the kind of
cognitive uncertainty, then when they
get the unexpected observations that bad
things don't happen, then it does
overwrite the likelihood under both
states, right? Um under both hidden of
both hidden contexts, and then it does
generalize, right? Um and that's um
that's actually uh consistent with this
kind of cool study that um
uh Sam Gershman um
has written some stuff about um
back in like 2015-ish. It's like been a
little while, but but where you can do
more or less the same thing with rats um
with like just classical conditioning
experiments where, you know, this is
kind of you know, you play a tone, they
get shocked, you know, like over and
over again with some probability. So now
you play the tone and they kind of jump
or freeze or do something implying that
they'll rock. Um and then the standard
thing to do during extinction is you
just present the tone over and over
again, and you don't show the shock at
all. Or you don't give them shock at
all. And so, then the responses slowly
die. Um but similar to with exposure
therapy, you bring the rats back a day
later, you play the tone again, and they
do have this kind of spontaneous
recovery is what it's called where they
start to have the fear response again.
Um which means they're doing basically
the same thing, right? The rats, too,
are just inferring, "Okay, I'm not sure
if I'm still in the safe context." Uh
So, so what they showed though was is
that if you do the extinction um if you
do the extinction
time course a little differently, um
then you can actually prevent this
spontaneous recovery. Um and the way
they did it is
instead of during extinction just
abruptly completely stopping the the
association between the tone and the
shock, what they did is they just said,
"Okay, for a little while, tone is asso-
associated with shock 90% of the time.
Okay. Now, for a while, tone is
associated with shock 80% of the time.
Okay. Now, 70% of the time."
They taper them off.
Yeah. So, and what that does, you can
kind of think about it is the prediction
errors are never that big, right? And if
the prediction errors are never that
big, then that's not good evidence for
the shift in context.
Right.
Right? And so, it does cause this slow
overriding, right? Of the original
likelihood function as opposed to
promoting the state inference thing. Um
and when they did it that way, and then
they tested the rats later, they didn't
have the spontaneous recovery like the
the fear responses didn't come back. Um
And that is fascinating. It's very it's
it's quite counterintuitive, though.
Mhm.
Because you Yeah, I think you would be
one would be under the presumption that
if you just kept providing
evidence,
you know, if you kept tying an
observation to a different state,
that would just become entrenched. But
it it does make sense that
that itself becomes this kind of
crystallized thing. And then, once you
take them out and put them back in, then
the previous one still has that
precision. That's that's that's really
fascinating. You also said something
very interesting there, which was um
it was kind of under the radar, but the
difference between
having a strong preference to be
somewhere or to have something or to be
something or whatever versus
uh
ha- like having a strong dispreference
not to be somewhere, be something, have
something. So, a positive versus a
double negative.
Mhm.
I've often found this in in active
inference. I don't think it's been
particularly well codified what the
difference is between those.
So, people will say, "Oh, um
I want to be um
37.8." Right? In some subpersonal way.
"I want to be 37.8° C,
and so I take action to restore that."
But, you could well cast as, "I don't
want to be
40° C." Right?
Yeah.
Is there a Is there a technical
difference between those?
Um so, I mean, one one thing that I
guess is a lot is kind of unique about
the way that active inference encodes
preferences compared to, you know, more
kind of like traditional formalisms like
reinforcement learning that cast things
explicitly in terms of reward function,
um is that
you know, strictly speaking, an active
inference agent isn't really trying to
maximize reward. They're trying to
minimize divergence from a target
distribution.
Right? And that actually has certain
interesting implications. Um but, one
one uh
one thing to consider with that, though,
is that is that um unlike in things like
reinforcement learning, um
all of your preferences
kind of constrain each other in the
sense that the whole distribution has to
add up to one.
Right? Um
so so uh you can
um so I think that
you will have to kind of relatively
speaking um
basically you will only be able to
specify relative preferences.
Um so so I think that so I think that if
you if you have a distribute a
preference distribution where the kind
of highest
mass is over, you know, like 38-ish
degrees, right? Then then the fact that
it kind of tails off on both sides
simultaneously guarantees that you
disprefer being above and below that. Um
so so I don't know explicitly whether or
not there is um
whether or not there's there's any way
to um encode those in a way that's
different. Um there are interesting
things you can do by putting kind of
like negative preferences for something
and positive preferences for another
thing. If there's like an observation
you can lock as kind of like the
baseline value of like zero. Um
when the thing gets normalized
um to turn it back into an actual
probability distribution, then then it
does still end up being kind of a
precise
uh
preference for one thing and
dispreference for the other and they do
still end up being relative to each
other. So so um and the main the main
thing that we tend to see when we do
like simulation stuff in those sorts of
setting is is it just tends to um
lead to this kind of like
anti-exploration
behavior um when when, you know, one
thing's really negative or it's kind of
like the uh
the uh agent is just kind of this like,
you know, better safe than sorry, you
know, sort of uh
sort of behavior.
Um but I um but I think
there are there should definitely be
ways of encoding those in terms of all
just kind of relative relative positive
values that end up normalizing to the
same distribution.
Cool. Yeah, I I think part of the reason
why I asked that is because I think it's
a point that you make in
uh the papers that you've written on
interoceptive inference,
which is that when uh we speak of sort
of so-called aberrant interoceptive
inference, a lot of papers are not very
clear whether they're talking about the
underweighting of priors or the
overweighting of the likelihood
distribution.
Sure.
Um I think part of the problem is people
think of uh precision weighting as a
necessary zero-sum game such that you
can't have both.
So, if I have
uh reduced precision over my likelihood,
by necessity, that will lead to
increased precision over my prior. If I
have decreased precision over my prior,
by necessity, that leads to an uptake in
the precision of the likelihood. But,
what you show, at least in this uh 2020
paper, the one that I read from PLoS um
where you did the interoceptive
perturbation condition, is that it isn't
the case.
So, where where do you think that kind
of false intuition comes from?
Oh, it comes It comes from It comes from
the fact that people usually, in the way
that they, at least in these more kind
of conceptual papers, um
comes in part from the fact that uh
these are under um
uh
they're talking about models that have
Gaussian assumptions with continuous
distributions.
Um cuz if you have if you just have uh
along a single dimension, right, if you
have like a distribution that defines
the likelihood function and a
distribution that defines the
um prior belief, then then there are,
right, when I turn up one or turn down
the other, then there's a bunch of
different ways that I can kind of
combine those things to lead to the same
posterior. Um so, it does become hard to
distinguish.
Um so, it depends on the dimensionality
and depends on whether you're talking
about continuous or categorical
distributions. Um so so, in in the in
the case of what we're doing, these are
discrete distributions, right? So, in in
discrete models, with the dimensionality
the way that we have it set up, uh
it makes
they makes clearly distinct behavioral
predictions, but
but in the in the kind of unidimensional
Gaussian
setup,
then you you do get this more
only the relative waiting matters.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That makes
sense.
Okay, so thus far, I know we we haven't
got too much time, but thus far, I know
we've kind of been speaking generally
about
perceptual updating and parameter
updating.
Mhm.
Um or parameter learning and belief
updating. But we also have structure
learning and active inference.
And
I think you make a really nice point to
say that sort of something like
introducing a concept to distinguish
between
or or to yes, to let's say split up a
concept that you had before. So, if I
had anger, now maybe I can turn that
into rage and fury.
Sure.
Um I think I believe you call that
emotional granularity.
Yeah, in the in the Yeah, in the emotion
in the emotional state inference
context, yeah, we would talk about that
in terms of granularity or uh
Yeah, that's usually the probably the
best way to talk about it, yeah.
It's a really fascinating concept
because it it it I think on on first
glance, it seems like a
it seems like a sort of
just linear benefit. The more emotional
gran- granularity I have, the better.
Um yeah, I mean, what that what the
direct relationship would be between
like the the number of you know, states
in the state space and uh and something
to do with gamma, I think is is going to
be fairly indirect, um but for a number
of reasons, but um I mean, I I think
with most things, right? I mean, the
general answer is going to be that um
it's not so much about complexity per se
as more complexity than necessary.
Yeah.
Right? So, so um right, you
you know, complexity adding complexity
is good if it increases accuracy, right?
So, so,
so, what it would mean, right, to be
more complex than necessary would be
that there's a mismatch to the actual
generative process. Um so, I think that
I think that the um
if you have more, right, if you're
over-fitting, right, to the to the
generative process, right, if you if
you're inventing more categories than
there actually are distinctions to make,
um then, obviously, it's going to be
problematic, right, because you're
you're going to think you have more
information than actually you do. Um
But but so long as but so long as you're
carving up your state space in a more
fine-grained way, and that actually does
add to the informativeness
of the information that your generative
model
is able to kind of pick up and then use
to inform policy selection, then then I
would expect it would be the more the
better, right? It's just the more So,
it's the the more accurate information
you have, the more informed policy
selection will be, right? So, so as long
as as long as
you have you're good at inferring the
right, you know, posterior over what
emotional state you're in, and each
emotional state that you kind of have
have acquired into your generative
model, um if if each of those does, in
fact, make unique
um um predictions about patterns of
current and future observations under
that state, then then yeah, I mean,
it'll be better just cuz it'll should,
right, on average, just make policy
selection more informed.
Right, right, right.
But um
Yeah. Thinking more broadly about the
distinction between structure learning
and parameter learning,
do you see these as bright dividing
lines,
or do you see them as being kind of
philosophically vague as to when
parameter learning becomes structure
learning?
Um you know, like I guess it's just it's
just tricky. I I like, you get in the
weeds on some of this stuff because
So, you do that's what we're here we're
here for the weeds.
People People use structural learning,
the term structural learning to mean
several different things, right? So, I
mean structural learning itself is is a
kind of like superordinate category with
a bunch of different kind of exemplar
things within it.
Um so, you know, I mean we did I don't
know if you saw this this is one paper
on structural learning specifically
that, you know, we put out a few years
ago where it was kind of like, you know,
people that, you know, there was just
like kind of a dumb example of people
trying to like learn like coarse-grained
or fine-grained, different types of like
birds and fish and stuff.
Why why
Right?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And uh and I mean, you know, so in that
it was like you could just learn like
these broad categories of bird and fish
or you could kind of like learn to carve
it up into specific types of birds,
specific types of fish, and they just
kind of each of those does it was
defined with with respect to specific
like patterns of covariance among
certain sorts of observable features,
right? Like wings versus gills and size
and color and things like that. But um
you know, and in in that particular
case, the way that like structural
learning was posed was in relation to
kind of like inferring how many states
need to be in your state space, right?
To account for account for data. Um and
so and so
um that has to do with kind of the setup
of the structure of the generative model
proper, right? Like how many how many
types of states, how many states, how
many how many how many state factors,
how many levels of states within each
state factor, etc. Um you know, so in
the in the
general POMDP scheme, that is
distinguishable from parameter learning
in the sense that parameters are usually
kind of um
the the values of the entries into the
matrices within, you know, things like
the likelihood function, transition etc.
Um that you update, but you update those
under the assumption that like, you
know, number of number of columns in the
in each matrix are are kind of fixed,
right?
Right.
So, so so if you're talking about kind
of this granularity kind of
fine-graining of of your of the concepts
that you have,
um then then there is a clear
distinction between
um
between um
those examples of parameter learning and
structure learning. But um but like I
said, there's other types of structure
learning and the actual implementation
of how you do structure learning also
matters because you know, in our
example, um
you know, we we use this kind of like
little trick, right? Where we just kind
of said, you know, we're we're actually
going to
you know, stick the matrices in as
though there's a bunch of these kind of
extra unused columns. You know, so we
didn't have to kind of like explicitly
add states to the state space. We just
kind of had a bunch of states that were
just kind of like sitting there silently
unused.
Yeah.
And then the way that and then the way
that the thing kind of worked was just
that
you know, what they meant to be unused
was the distributions were just
completely flat. Right? So, they didn't
predict really anything unique about the
observations.
Um and so and so the way that that would
work is just that um
more or less that if you got some
pattern of observations that was
consistent with one of the kind of
informative likelihood functions under a
kind of state that you already had,
um
then the posterior would be precise over
that state and you know, you would have
a basically zero posterior over all the
unused columns and so you wouldn't have
any parameter updating under those
columns.
But um but if you had some pattern of
observations and they were really
inconsistent with any of the informative
mappings that you had, then effectively
what that would do is it would mean that
the flat mappings would would better
explain the data.
Right. Right. Right. Right. Right.
And you know, and as soon as like the
flat mapping better explains the data,
then you end up with a precise posterior
over one of these unused columns, right?
Whichever one happens to explain it
best. And then you just start learning
the parameters under that new column,
right? So So and then you that's just a
way of learning a new informative
mapping. So it's kind of like
effectively now you have a new column,
you've expanded your state space, right?
Yep.
And you could you could do that a little
bit more explicitly than we did by
writing in some additional function that
like explicitly, you know, just like
added new columns to the state space or
something as opposed to just having
these unused ones sitting around.
Right.
Right. But my point is is is that
the the relationship between structural
learning and parameter learning is
very the the the they're very tightly
intertwined in in that case, right?
Because like when you start learning the
parameters like the the thing that leads
you to start learning parameters is the
the exact thing that is causing you to
do structural learning.
Right. Right. Right. Right. Right. Yes,
exactly.
So But But again, that's one
That's one implementation, right? So I'm
saying that that won't be true. That
doesn't need to be true um
generically, but that will be true in
some cases.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Well, and it
seems like they all
to Yeah, they all lean on one another in
some kind of recursive manner where you
can't really have structural learning
without
learning the parameters in, you know, of
that structure in the first place, nor
the belief updating that allows you to
kind of get there in the first place,
right? In a dynamic system, in a
dynamically changing system.
Yeah, I mean, I think I think it's just
And again, I can't I can't really say
with confidence how well this will
generalize to other cases of structural
learning or or even just other kind of
generative model setups and things like
that, but but yeah, at least in this
case it's kind of
you have to
you have to effectively infer that the
the current informative parameters and
parameter based mappings that you have
are not doing a good job of explaining
something,
and then end up with a very low
posterior distribution um
over
or a posterior that assigns a very low
probability to any of the
states you currently have in your state
space and then
and then so it's like you get the right
posterior based on you know that based
on the fact that your current parameters
are not good explain you know don't
provide good explanations for the data
and then
by starting to update different set of
parameters you end up leading to doing
something that is effectively structural
learning. So it's yeah they're just very
yeah it is all just very kind of tightly
connected.
Yeah yeah yeah. Well it'd be interesting
to see if you could sort of disambiguate
them you know in the model like whether
you could just have
I do I guess that
Yeah conceptually though I think that's
tricky right because you somehow have to
say I need structural learning only
because
Well exactly. Well that's what I meant
kind of by this recursive nature. I mean
I don't know if recursion's even the
right way of talking about it. It might
be sort of nesting
um
in some sense that belief updating
drives parameter updating which like
ultimately feeds into structural
learning.
Yeah.
Cool.
So final question. Big question. You got
this paper coming out the imperial the
so-called empirical status of predictive
coding.
Uh and active inference but yeah.
And active inference. I yes is that the
name is that the whole name of the
paper?
Mhm. Yeah.
Um
it's a sort of classic critique
leveraged at active inference that it's
self-contained and it's an echo chamber
and it's a lot of philosophers and
mathematicians kind of spitballing these
fancy ideas but it doesn't
this is a common critique I'm not saying
it's true.
Oh okay. Yeah yeah.
Yeah yeah yeah. Oh well it would be it
would be odd if it if I were to
promulgate that position as the host of
this podcast.
Oh no no no sorry. I thought I thought
you were saying that that was the the
thrust of our paper.
No no no no no. I'm saying it's a common
critique from those on the outside.
I don't remember saying all that.
No, no, no, you no, I know you didn't.
But it's it's a common critique at
least. I mean, that might be uh over
simplifying the critique, but that
you know, this theory of everything
is overgeneralizing and it doesn't have
evidential an evidential basis.
Where
having done this sort of deep dive into
the empirical status of active inference
and predictive coding,
what are the conclusions that you guys
have drawn?
Um
I mean, I I just think I kind of think
at the end of the day, I mean, it
amounts to be something kind of similar
to what I think you'll see in a lot of
review papers for most things, right?
This is this is just that there's a lot
of stuff where more work needs to be
done
Sure.
to be for it to be definitive. I mean,
that's kind of like the the very
oversimplified conclusion. I mean, I
would say that I I mean, one thing that
that I hope that we tried to make clear
um is just it's more that like there's
just a lots of different levels of
claims with respect to both predictive
coding and active inference. And they
all kind of need to be tested in a way
that's a little bit at least partially
independent of each other, right? So, I
mean, especially in the philosophy
literature, people will even talk about
really broad like categories like, you
know, just like predictive processing,
you know, quote unquote. But like
I mean, if you want to move from that
down to stuff that is actually testable,
um requires
a bunch of There's a bunch of kind of
layers that you have to kind of work
through to get there, right? So, you can
have say, "Okay, well, predictive
processing is a very generic idea that
in some way
one of the main things the brain does is
predict stuff, I guess."
Right? And that's like, "Okay, well, you
know, uh two of the most kind of like
prominent, but certainly not the only
possible categories for that are like
predictive coding and perception and
active inference and action." But then
even from there, right? I mean, like
predictive coding makes particular
explanatory makes particular predictions
if what you're talking about is um
something about the uh the the the the
predictive coding algorithm, right? As
defined, right? Which is which doesn't
necessarily need to make predictions at
the level of the kind of like neuro-
neurobiological implementation, right?
So, and same thing same thing with
active inference, right? Active
inference Firstly, okay, well, what type
of active inference are we talking
about? Are we talking about like the you
know, continuous state spaces or we
talking about discrete state spaces and
you know, like are we talking about uh
you know, commitments
related to, you know, some of these like
claims about, you know, the gamma stuff
and dopamine or, you know, are we just
talking about things about categorical
state inference and that and that that
depends on minimizing variational free
energy um through like a variational
message passing scheme, right? And okay,
are we actually hypothesizing
variational message passing or are we
hypothesizing marginal message passing
or are we hypothesizing that the
implementation draws or that that the
algorithm is doing some sort of like
belief propagation thing, right? And and
then even there, right? That's still all
just at the algorithmic level. And then
you have to say, okay, well, if I commit
to some algorithm, right? If I commit to
POMDP, discrete state space, you know,
this particular generative model
structure for this task um
you know, with this you know, with this
message passing scheme as I said, then
all right, there's like probably at
least like 20 ways that you could set up
a neural network right? To solve that,
right? So, then you also have to have a
hypothesis about, okay, what am I what
what implementation, you know, am I am I
testing, right? And what are the
predictions of that implementation?
Right? So, if I'm doing something at the
neuroscience level, then I must say,
okay, it's kind of this very kind of
hierarchical thing where it's like, you
know, this particular neural prediction
that follows from this neural hypothesis
neural implementation that follows from
this specific narrow algorithmic
commitment, you know, like from this
larger kind of framework, you know, you
know what I'm saying? So, it's like
You stop making exclusions.
Yeah, so testing so testing these things
is
what it even means to be testing these
things is is is kind of complicated
because um by the time you can actually
get down to something that's empirically
testable, um you've narrowed it down a
ton.
Um right. Right.
And ruling out one implementation
doesn't falsify
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
active processing, nor does it falsify
active inference, right? It just means
you ruled out that a particular
implementation of a particular
algorithm,
you know, within the active inference
framework, etc. So, it's like, okay,
well, now on testing like implementation
hypothesis two.
Yes.
So, it's a you know, so that that's
tough, right? So, then
um but a lot of, you know, but a lot of
what's been done is much more um well, I
should say with with predictive coding a
lot of stuff's been done at the at the
neural level. With active inference,
it's very minimal's been done in terms
of like neuroscience
Um
neuro- neuroscientific studies. Like
Philip Schordinger had a cool study in
like 2015 where they did um where they
did uh some of the um some of the uh
like midbrain dopamine
Um
results in relation to um some of the uh
the beta updating stuff. I mean, it's
called alpha in that paper, so like
slightly older formalism, but but same
basic idea.
Um
But so
You know, so there's that, and then, you
know, there's kind of like with
predictive coding, for example,
Um you know, I think
I think many people would say that one,
you know, one specific commitment at
least to kind of like vanilla
Um
forms of, you know, hypothesis
predictive coding architectures is like,
okay, well, prediction errors get passed
upward, predictions get passed downward,
you know, there's kind of these separate
populations of prediction units and
prediction error units.
Yeah.
Typically, it's like, okay, well, the
predictionary units are in like cortical
layer two three, and you know, like in
the deep, you know, prediction units are
in, you know, pyramidal cells in layer
five six five and six. Um, you know, but
then, you know, when you actually look
at like some of these more complicated
like canonical microcircuit models and
things like that that that really
explore in detail, right, how you would
do predictive coding um, in a way that
would kind of match up to the actual
like cortical columnar architecture
structures that we know about, you know,
from like microanatomical you know,
actual brain studies. Like, you know, I
mean, it becomes way more complicated,
right? You have like specific roles of
like granule cells, and then you have
kind of like the sorts of predictions
and prediction errors that are
hypothesized to be like passed around
through like different interneurons, and
then how those pass signals up, and you
know, it turns out that like like uh,
prediction error signals need to be
inhibitory, but the between column
connections are all glutamatergic, and
so they're excitatory. Right? You need
to basically have any prediction error
signal be excitatory, but then pass
through some inhibitory interneuron
uh, at the receiving end to then turn it
into,
right, an inhibitory thing. And then,
you know, as opposed to the simple kind
of vanilla predictive predictive coding
architectures or or algorithm, um,
the most of the canonical micro circuit
circuit stuff has been pitched in terms
of these um, more kind of like
temporally extended versions of
predictive coding where you have like at
each level, you're not just represent-
representing a hidden state, but you're
also representing what they call like a
hidden cause. Um, and the the
distinction between a hidden state and a
hidden cause is is that like one of them
actually predicts the dynamics of the
states at the level below. Um, so it's
kind of like hidden states to say like
hidden state is or now I'm mixing up
which one it is.
One of them, either hidden state or
hidden cause, uh, Uh, I mean, this is
just very bargainedy,
Yeah,
and just arbitrary choice of terminology
to a certain extent, but but
well, I'll say it the way that's a
little more intuitive to me, but but so
if it's if hidden state is like bird
singing a song, right, at one level,
then, you know, I just have some
representation about, you know,
probability of bird singing song or
something like that, fairly abstract.
But then that then sends a signal to
represent this hidden cause thing, and
what the hidden cause thing does is send
predictions down to the level below
about like some series of notes, right,
like some sequence
to the level where the hidden state at
that level is like representing what
note is happening at a unit, you know,
at some at some time period. But so so
even there, right, those are both
predictive coding, but those are two
different predictive coding
different predictive coding theories.
Um, so
so anyway, I mean, so I just just to
point out fairly long-windedly that
there's just a lot of complexity in in
specifying what you're in fact even
testing. Um, but the um but the main the
main thing I mean, the main kind of
broad strokes result was just that um in
predictive coding, I mean, there's
certainly nothing that rules it out,
right? I mean, there's um there's some
cool, you know, results probably like
the strongest results that um would
suggest something like that has to be
going on is um like findings related to
like omission responses, right, where
brain activity increases when you expect
to get a to get a stimulus and the
stimulus is absent.
Yeah.
Right, so like if a stimulus is
stimulus comes, right, it should
trigger some activity under a
feedforward sort of hypothesis, but the
absence of something should never
trigger.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. That's just a little
classic
so said Montague.
Yeah, you know, that's a
But um but the but omission responses
and, you know, other things like error
related negativity and a lot of the the
kind of more standard stuff that looks
like prediction and prediction error
responses that are consistent with
predictive coding. Um, you know, they
certainly don't, you know, provide
really precise evidence that there's
like, you know, particular layer two,
three neurons that are representing
prediction errors and five, six ones
that are going to predictions. There are
a couple cool studies that have come out
like super recently though that do look
like with like laminar um fMRI and
things like that that do are starting to
support these kind of like distinct
populations of error neurons and
predictive neurons. So, that stuff's
exciting. Um
It's all very exciting. Well, it's you
know, it's a niche, but at least it's
it's incorporating it well, at least it
sounds like
from your investigation it it's
beginning to well,
I'd like to think that it's beginning to
hone down on some specific ways that we
can get more precise
hypotheses and ways of testing those
hypotheses. I I mean, it's it's it's
it's you know,
if the you know, the three the the main
papers 2009, 2010,
fair enough that it's taken a little
while to get its
you know,
it it to get to stop reaching that kind
of finer precision that that that level
of granularity, that level of
I think you know,
to my eyes some of that philosophical
work needed to be done just to lay out
exactly the parameters, if you pardon
the pardon, of
the explorandum of what we're trying to
find out. So, I don't know, it sounds
promising to me. It sounds exciting.
Yeah, I know. I mean, I think yeah, I
mean, certainly I think I think we need
to hold things to a given I mean, as you
say, right? Given that these um you
know, these particular theories are you
know, much more recent, right? Than
other like, you know, computational
neuroscience theories that have had a
lot more time, right? To be to be
tested. Um so, so yeah, I mean, I think
we need to be fair given the amount of
time that that um you know, these things
have been uh these things have even been
been around to test and the you know,
the number of groups that have been
motivated to you know, put together
studies and get them funded right to do
these sorts of tests. Um absolutely. Um
you know, I mean in and with um and with
respect to uh you know, active
inference, I mean that's even more true,
right? I mean the the actual kind of
like empirically testable like
behavioral modeling, you know, sorts of
you know, sufficient sufficiently
precise right formalisms or um you know,
like the kind of stuff that we do. You
know, what that's been around like what
since like 2017?
Yeah, yeah.
ish and and it's you know, been kind of
evolving from there and and so um and so
you know, much much less time even and
um you know, I mean I think there's a
lot of things that you know, I mean we
still need to do I mean along the
approach that we're taking, right? So I
mean primarily you know, what we've you
know, the the stuff that we reviewed
that you know, that we've done with uh
you know, empirical like trying to find
empirical support for active inference
probably hasn't really up until now done
a good enough job of doing model
comparison against competing models. You
know, our focus has been largely um kind
of like computational psychiatry
focused. So the idea has been more okay,
let's define a set of active inference
models, fit those models to behavior and
see where we can find differences in
those models between clinical groups and
healthy groups, right? So we can show
that like in an absolute sense, right?
Like active inference models can explain
data pretty you know, reasonably well,
right? Like
Yeah.
on a on a model on a task where like
chance action probability would be like
1/3, you know, like these models can
explain behavior with you know,
assigning probabilities around like you
know, between like 0.65 and 0.7
something, right? So I mean it's it's a
you know, much much better than chance
and not not too different than what
you'd see in in other computational
neuroscience studies. Um but you know,
that hasn't that doesn't directly
compare active inference models um to
you know, other classes of models,
right? That have already been around,
right? And so that's a little bit more
of the kind of thing we've been trying
to do recently is to more definitively
kind of say, you know, how much, you
know, can we find
evidence for active inference models
that is not equal evidence for other
models that have been around for longer.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. No, that that sounds
sounds absolutely worthwhile. And yeah,
I think you're
I think some people
you know,
they don't they almost don't want to do
that because if it turns out that an RL
model does better than active inference
model, then like let's just throw in the
towel. But
um
Yeah, even even that I think needs to be
kind of like understood with a little
bit of a grain of salt though because
because um well, you can you can worry
that that um
that
there are tasks where the tasks are
simple enough that an RL model will do a
perfectly good job explaining what's
going on. And an active inference model
would basically predict the exact same
thing, right? As a reinforcement
learning model. And in that case, you
know, maybe the active inference model
is more complicated and so like the RL
model would win. But you know, I mean
that's just because in those contexts,
they're you know, they have a certain
isomorphism, you know, the
to them. So I think I think you have to
you have to
make these comparisons in tasks where um
like a a simpler model certainly could
explain behavior equally well, but but
there's there's reason to think other
models that that there could be the
patterns of dynamics in the in the
choice behavior that um that could
differentiate, right? Active inference
models from reinforce from reinforce
I like it, Ryan. I like it. You're
staying true to the to the field. I like
it. It's good.
That loyalty is much needed. But no, I I
I I really do admire the the
intellectual rigor and the academic
rigor. It's um it's much needed. Uh
Yeah, and I wouldn't and I wouldn't want
to like say, you know, like our stuff
and only our stuff. I mean, there are
other people that are doing, you know,
and very recently that have been doing
really cool stuff. Like there's this um
like the first author was something like
Gibson or something like that. I can't
remember. Tim Gibson maybe. I I don't
quote me on that, but but they did this
really cool um
um study where they took like these two
um a couple or maybe it was like four
I think it was yeah, four different like
publicly available data sets um from uh
on the two-step task. Um two-step task
is a very kind of classic
um RL task that like basically was
designed specifically to estimate how
much people are doing more kind of like
model-based versus model-free um sort of
planning. Um and um and I mean, super
widely used. I mean, people have shown
really cool stuff with that, you know,
like like uh developmentally, you know,
like kids as they get older start to
look more model-based, you know.
Right. Right. Right.
You know, basically means they actually
start to use an actual transition
function.
Yeah. Yeah.
Right? Or right? Um
um and um
but um but, you know, so what they did
is they they took, right? Like the
classic, you know, widely used um
model-based model-free kind of combo
model that typically gets used for um um
for that task. And then they also fit
that same data to um to uh um like a
competing active inference model. Um and
um in two of the four data sets, um
model comparison was kind of equivocal.
Um and in the other two data sets,
active inference models did win in model
comparison um for that. And these are
pretty large data sets. And again,
that's a very It's another, you know,
very kind of classic task. So the fact
that uh
the fact that
active inference did a better job of
explaining two-step task behavior, I
thought, you know, I thought that was
actually like incredibly
No, well, yeah. I mean, when it starts
influencing
better better than what we've done in
terms of actually testing active
inference models.
Yeah, well when it starts entering into
the space where others should dominate,
that's you know, that's when you know
it's onto something.
Ryan, I know you're you're the world's
busiest man
filling out forms and
and all sorts. And so I'm incredibly
appreciative. We've just hit the hour
and a half mark.
Well, thank you so much for for giving
me your time.
And educating me. I feel I mean every
time I have people on, whether they're
philosophers, neuroscientists,
mathematicians, and so on, it's always
such a pleasure to to learn more about
what the work they're doing. In terms of
what you've got coming up, so this paper
that is coming out in the future,
that's out. People can read it although
it's supposedly out in the future.
What else what else have you got coming
up? Where can people find your work? How
can people reach out to you if they're
interested in asking questions or
collaborating, whatever it might be.
Oh yeah, I mean, you know, anything on
our you know, our lab website.
You know, or email me, you know, like
our our smith at luriainstitute.org.
You know,
feel free.
Yeah, we'll we'll link the we'll link
the paper.
You know, the typical routes.
All the all the standards, the standard
stuff. I mean my email is also typically
the one that's like the corresponding
author email on most papers. So,
you know, and there's certainly
lots of
lots of ways to get in contact with me
if you so desire, but
Great. Well, we'll make sure we link
everything below.
So, thank you once again from me and the
institute. It's been really really fun.
Sure, no. Thank you very much for having
me.